Today we finish קינים Kinnim and there is really only one little
difficult final of these complicated cases, not even so complicated to do
and then it'll be a quick wrap up and we will also
start the new מסכת Masechet which is תמיד. Tamid. So we pick
up—תמיד, Tamid, I mean תמיד. Tamid. I made a mistake yesterday, תמיד
Tamid comes first, sorry about that. But anyway,
okay, so we pick up—yesterday we started—we had the case. Let me
just describe it again.
Basically it was a woman who said she was going to bring
a נדר Neder together
with her קרבן Korban of יולדת. Yoledes. She said of a particular
type, she forgot if she said תור Tor or בני יונה, Bnei
Yonah, she forgot what she did. So if she forgot what she
said, she forgot what she did, she's going to have to do
all that again.
And—but she also said she was going to bring it together with
her חטאת, Chatus, with her קרבן Korban for יולדת, Yoledes, which means
as this is being understood—by the way, you're not surprised to hear
that there's a big debate of the ראשונים Rishonim how to explain
this because there are a lot of assumptions that have to be
read in to make sense of this—but the way it is being
interpreted is that that means that all the עולות Olos have to
be together: the two עולות Olos of her נדר Neder plus the
עולה Olah of her חובה, Chovah, of her קרבן יולדת. Korban Yoledes.
So she said she was going to bring it all together. So
because she doesn't know what she did and the כהן Kohen doesn't
know what he did or whatever and she'll have to do all
of that again. She'll have to do all of that again.
She's going to have to bring her, you know,
two עולות Olos from תור Tor and two from בני יונה. Bnei
Yonah. She doesn't know what she said, she doesn't know what she
did, it could be that nothing was brought and so on. That's
what she's going to have to bring because of just the נדר
Neder part. But she said she's going to bring it together with
the—her obligatory קרבן. Korban. Now here, this was done yesterday. We don't
know exactly what was done, right? That was done the day before,
but this isn't together with it. So the only way she's going
to get this together with her obligatory עולה Olah is to also
bring another bird as an עולה. Olah. Now that can be whatever
type she wants, that doesn't have to be of a particular type.
This one she said one type, she didn't remember which. And since
we don't know even what was done, that has to be done
again. She said with an עולה, Olah, with the עולה Olah there
was done on the previous day. Together she has to bring four
and one more and five. Okay, that's the first part. We're going
to go now read the more complicated cases. Okay, so
the חטאת Chatus was brought, but she can't bring a חטאת Chatus
again. Right, but she doesn't have to. We're assuming that when she
says "I'm going to bring it together with my obligatory קרבן," Korban,
the together just means all the עולות Olos are together because that's
the only stuff that's done. But the חטאת Chatus has to be—the
עולות Olos presumably were done on the same day. Doesn't have to
be done on the same day?
Does not have to be on the same day?
I guess. All right, so now, so now, that's—so we're going to
pick up, we're going to pick up six lines from the bottom,
six lines from the bottom, last one on the line. כנדרה, Kavenidra,
so she says she's going to do it all together with her
obligatory קרבן, Korban, which we say means the עולות Olos are all
together, צריכה להביא עוד חמש פרידין. Tzericha lehavi od chamesh peridin.
She has to bring five. Now that is ממין אחד. Mimin echad.
That is if it's all of the same מין Min or all
of the same species. Because here she doesn't know which one she
said. So obviously that's not what happened. All of these were either
תור Tor or בני יונה, Bnei Yonah, she just doesn't know what.
Okay, so all of these were מין אחד, Min echad, then that
leads to five as we said. However, if it is משני מינים,
Mishnei minim, if what she brought yesterday was of different types and
she doesn't also know how that was brought, תביא שש, Tavi shesh,
six.
Why? Why would this ever lead to more than this? Isn't this
everything? No, because you remember the הלכה Halacha is that by
a חטאת Chatus and an עולה—the Olah same way as we learned
before by two עולות, Olos, by a נדר Neder pair, by a
חובה Chovah pair—anyway, one determines the other. We said by a חטאת
Chatus and an עולה, Olah, the מין Min of the חטאת Chatus
determines the מין Min of the עולה. Olah. If the חטאת Chatus
is a תור, Tor, the עולה Olah has to be a תור.
Tor. If the חטאת Chatus is בני יונה, Bnei Yonah, the עולה
Olah has to be בני יונה. Bnei Yonah. You remember that? They
have to be the same and the חטאת Chatus determines. Okay, so
because she doesn't know what happened here yesterday, she doesn't know was
it all תור. Tor. If she knows it was all תור Tor
but
I don't know what I vowed, then this you bring both, and
this would have to be a תור. Tor. But she doesn't know
what the חטאת Chatus was. Was that a תור Tor or בני
יונה? Bnei Yonah? I don't know, I brought different things, I don't
know what in the end the כהן Kohen did. So this has
to be one for תור Tor and one for בני יונה Bnei
Yonah because this has to make sure that the עולה Olah matches
what the חטאת Chatus was yesterday. Okay, so in this case, this
she has to bring because she doesn't know her vow was fulfilled
and she doesn't know what her vow was, תור Tor or בני
יונה, Bnei Yonah, and she has to bring two עולות Olos because
she doesn't know what the חטאת Chatus was yesterday and the עולות
Olos are going to have to match.
But presumably the עולה Olah was done right yesterday too, right?
What?
If we assume the חטאת Chatus was
done—it doesn't matter, it doesn't matter. No, because if she... Because you
know what I mean? It doesn't count as obligatory, it's not.
That's an interesting question. You're saying that even if somehow her vow
required it, wouldn't it by definition have יוצא yotzei her חובה, chovah,
and then she no longer actually do that? How could she redefine?
It's a good question. It's a good question unless you say that
it becomes, it's defined also in the reverse direction. Once you say
her נדר neder has to be with her, with her you know
with her חובה, chovah, in a way it was also somehow making
her חובה chovah dependent on her נדר. neder. But it's a very
good question. That's a good question. Okay, so that's that case and
now, and this is it, here we come, home stretch. Okay? So
I hope you were with me until now because then this is,
this is not so much more complicated. Now let's take a look.
השתי מינין שהביאה שש. Hashtei minin shehevia shesh. נתנה למעלה Nasna l'maalah
ואין ידוע מה נתנה. v'ein yaduah mah nasna. והלך הכהן ועשה ואין
ידוע מה עשה. V'halach hakohen v'asah v'ein yaduah mah asah. Now
it sounds like pretty much what we've been saying until now, right?
She doesn't remember what she gave, the כהן kohen doesn't know what
she, you know, you know, doesn't remember which one he did above,
what he did below. The only way this scenario is really different,
which isn't spelled out clearly here, is that the כהן kohen as
opposed to the past where we said he did half up and
half below and he just doesn't remember which he did where and
so on, here we're saying he doesn't remember what the heck he
did. He could have done it all above, all below, and so
on. Now, the question is why would that make a difference? I
mean she seems to have done absolutely everything possible by standard, right?
But no, here's what we, you have to bring one more in
this case. Why?
צריכה להביא עוד פרידין. Tzrichah l'havi od preidin. ארבע לנדרה, Arba l'nidrah,
four for her נדר, neder, that's we said before, right? Two תור
tor and two בני יונה. bnei yonah. ושנים לחובתה Ushnayim l'chovatah and
two for her obligatory עולה olah we mean by that. Well we've
already said that, two for her obligatory עולה. olah. So it's one
more, וחטאת אחת. v'chatas achas. She has to bring a חטאת. chatas.
Why does she have to bring the חטאת chatas here?
Because since the כהן kohen could have done everything above, it could
be that no
חטאת chatas was brought, right? If he did everything above, no חטאת
chatas was brought, so she has to bring a חטאת. chatas. Okay,
and even though she's bringing a חטאת chatas though, it could be
that the חטאת chatas was done below, that there was a חטאת
chatas done below. If the חטאת chatas was done below, then that
determines what the עולה olah has to be. So you have to
bring two עולות olos in the possibility that a חטאת chatas was
done below and you need to match what the חטאת chatas was.
But you have to also bring the חטאת chatas in the possibility
that
everything was done above.
Okay, so that's seven. Okay, that wasn't so hard. דף כה עמוד
א, Daf chaf-hei amud aleph, בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer, בן
עזאי Ben Azzai says שתי חטאות, shtei chatos, two חטאות. chatos.
Why? Because if you'll remember, בן עזאי Ben Azzai said a day
or two ago that it's not that the חטאת chatas determines the
מין min of the עולה, olah, it's that whichever was done first
determines the second one. So he says whatever was done first determines
the second, he says you've got to bring two עולות olos in
case the חטאת chatas was done first and then the עולה olah
has to match and you don't know what it has to match
so it has to bring two. But you also have to bring
two חטאות. chataos. Why? Because it's possible the עולה olah was done
first, right? If possible everything was done above, the עולה olah was
done, the
חטאת chatas has to match it and you don't know which kind
it was. So that's how you're going to get according to him
eight. And with that, and with that we end all of the
permutations and we have a nice little אגדתא agadata to wrap up.
Oh these really helped. They did, they did not help me at
all but I'm glad.
No, I know they really helped the diagram. Okay, because I didn't
get to hear you.
All right. So now let's, we have to, there was a חטאת,
chatas, those other two at the
very beginning those last two חטאות.
chatos. Yeah, does one have to be
a תור tor and the other have
to be a בן יונה?
ben yonah? Yeah, yeah, that's exactly, and what these are are combinatorics
problems, which we learned in grad, I didn't like the course but
I did learn that in grad school.
Okay, so now
let's
bring it all up front.
Okay, now a little wrap-up here. Now what you have to realize
is, although this מסכת maseches perhaps came right after מעילה, Meilah, it
really is the last מסכת maseches of סדר קדשים. Seder Kodshim.
And as such, what a lot of מסכתות masechtos do is they
end with a little דברי אגדתא divrei agadata at the end. The
רמב"ם Rambam actually follows that pattern. If you look at the רמב"ם
Rambam at the end of each one of his 14 ספרים, sefarim,
not his individual הלכות, halachos, although he has some those too, עבודה,
Avodah, קדשים, Kodshim, and so on, at the end of each one
he ends with like an אגדתא agadata piece. So anyway, let's take
a look.
What was that repetition of what she mixed up?
What's happening with them? The ones over there, they were already brought
on the מזבח mizbeach the day before. They brought yesterday. We just
don't know what happened, so we have to do it all again
because we can't count on any of them being good. Okay, I
know exactly what was, so מידות midos and then, I'll talk about
them, I'll talk about them.
This is, the basic point is that the order of מסכת... maseches...
The order of מסכתות Masechtot goes by the size, the number of
פרקים. Perakim. The bigger number of פרקים, Perakim, the מסכתא Masechta with
a larger number of פרקים Perakim comes before. However, in the וילנא
ש"ס, Vilna Shas, they sometimes reorganize it for more logical flow, so
for example,
I didn't give this example yesterday about I think I did, anyway
maybe I gave it on שבת. Shabbos. The real order in מועד
Moed for example is יומא, Yoma, סוכה, Sukkah, ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
Which is crazy. יומא, Yoma, סוכה, Sukkah, ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? But
because but but that's the order of פרקים. Perakim. Ten you know
eight פרקים Perakim for יומא, Yoma, five for סוכה, Sukkah, four for
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Anyway, we have the order ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, יומא, Yoma, סוכה Sukkah because that's chronological. I do not know
why קינים Kinnim was put before תמיד Tamid and מדות. Middot. I
mean they're all little מסכתות, Masechtot, why not go in order? I
have no idea. But anyway, this in the סדר משנה Seder Mishnah
comes last. So let's take a look. אמר רבי יהושע. Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua. So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said, זהו שאמרו. Zehu she-ameru. Oh
this whole thing how you get all these crazy permutations and in
the end wind up with seven birds. That's what they said, כשהוא
חי קולו אחד וכשהוא מת קולו שבעה. Keshehu chai kulo echad u-keshehu
met kulo shivah. When something is alive, it has one voice, and
when it dies it has seven voices. So apparently this was like
some saying, which what does that mean? And they didn't know, was
like a little bit of a riddle. And he says, oh you
know that's meant to indicate this case. Of course when it started,
it started with four birds. It didn't start with one bird that
led to seven. It only started with four birds that led to
seven. But anyway he says he wants to tie it into this
case that we just said in our משנה. Mishnah. And now however
the משנה Mishnah goes on to say maybe a more straightforward interpretation
of that little aphorism. כיצד, Keitzad,
how is this? קולו שבעה, Kulo shivah, now we're now switching to
talk about a about a cow, okay? So כיצד קולו שבעה, Keitzad
kulo shivah, how when a cow is alive, you know it moos,
it has one voice, when it dies it has seven voices? How
is that? שתי קרניו לשני חצוצרות, Shtei karanav lishnei chatzotzerot, its two
its two horns for חצוצרות Chatzotzerot for two trumpets. Now what does
that mean trumpet? It could mean some because trumpets are supposed to
be of silver. ועשית לך שתי חצוצרות כסף. Ve-aseita lecha shtei chatzotzerot
kesef. So there's a debate. Some say that חצוצרות Chatzotzerot here means
שופרות. Shofarot. There's actually a גמרא Gemara that says cow ear? That's
a good point maybe we're talking about a ram. Okay that's a
good point, I said a cow. Okay, say a ram. Say a
ram,
good point. Okay, anyway, some say it's talking about about a שופר,
Shofar, some oh because it's right, it says צמרו. Tzemero. Yeah thank
you okay right right you're right. Okay it's going to say wool,
so it is, it's a sheep or a ram, good point. Both
points well taken. Okay, anyway, so it could be a שופר, Shofar,
others say that the silver trumpets were the ones that the כהנים
Kohanim used for you know that were in במדבר Bamidbar they talk
about gathering the camp and so on, but the ones that the
לויים Levi'im used for musical accompaniment and for musical instruments, those could
also have been horns. You know animal horns, they didn't have to
be silver. Not clear, at least could. Okay, so there is a
debate what it means by חצוצרות Chatzotzerot here, does it mean שופר
Shofar for ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah or does it mean for the
לויים? Levi'im? Okay, but yes thank you we're talking about a ram.
שתי שוקיו לשני חלילים, Shtei shokav lishnei chalilim, its two side bones
would be used for two flutes, I guess you could make it
from the hollow of those bones. עורו לתוף, Oro letof, you use
its skin for a a tambourine, is that what it's called or
whatever, a drum, something of that type.
מעיו לנבלים, Me'av linevelim, its its stomach, its intestines for a for
a lyre. A lyre is apparently a sort of like a stringed
instrument. Right, like catgut. Catgut actually comes
from not cats, right, what is it, pig intestines? Some type of
intestine, not cat. Maybe cow intestine, I think. So they're mostly steel
now. Are they? Anyway so you use you use that for נבלים.
Nevelim. נבלים Nevelim are presumably some guitar like instrument like a lyre.
בני מעיו Benei me'av which are you know בני מעיו Benei me'av
is like the stomach, בני מעיו Benei me'av is like the
intestines, לכינורות, Lachinnorot, for harp strings, same idea except maybe a different
quality of string.
Wait what's the difference between מעיו Me'av and בני מעיו? Benei me'av?
I think מעיו Me'av is the stomach and בני מעיו Benei me'av
is like the intestines.
That's what it says in Artscroll.
There you go.
ויש אומרים אף צמרו לעשות תכלת. Ve-yesh omrim af tzemero la'asot techelet.
So that's seven by the way if you count them. You know
you've got two horns, two two flutes,
a tambourine, a lyre and a harp. That's seven. And some say
you can use the wool, so we're talking clearly about a sheep,
you use the wool for תכלת. Techelet. Well that's very nice that
you can use the מצוה Mitzvah ציצית Tzitzit with the wool but
what does that have to do with voices and sounds? So they
so they say that it's referring to the fact that the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, the מעיל תכלת, Me'il techelet, had at the bottom
little bells. And that would make a sound. Of course the reason
not so good is because it wasn't the תכלת Techelet that make
the sound, it was the bell that was making the sound. Okay,
so that is a little has nothing to do with what we
said, but this little aphorism about one turning into seven, which was
tried to tie it into our discussion about the birds and now
we have maybe a more simple interpretation about what that little aphorism
meant. And now we end with the real big אגדתא Aggad'ta and
tell me if you can if you can figure out what this
has to do with our מסכת. Masechet. רבי שמעון הקשיא אומר. Rabbi
Shimon Hakashia omer.
רבי שמעון
הקשיא
Rabbi
Shimon Hakashia says, זקני עם הארץ, Ziknei am ha-aretz, the old people
of the of the... of the non-educated class, כל זמן שמזקינין, kol
zman shemazkinin, the older they
get, דעתן מטורפת עליהם, da'atan m'terefet aleihem, their intelligence or
their thoughts become more
confused, שנאמר, shenemar, מסיר שפה לנאמנים וטעם זקנים יקח, Meisir safa l'ne'emanim
v'ta'am zkeinim yikach, God takes away the speech from the trustworthy so
it might be a particular כלל klal not talking about the normal
way of the world, but anyway the point is the end of
the פסוק pasuk and the sense from elders will be removed. So
sometimes people get old, there's a dementia's a pretty common, I think
that they say. What is it? I heard a statistic, I don't
know if it's correct, that like over like in people over 80
I think or over 75, 50% have some form of dementia. Does
that sound like it could be true?
It's probably over, it's over 90 and it's about 45%. I've published
on this.
Oh really? There you go. Okay. So, so for a lot of
people when you get older obviously it's a real, it's a real
רחמנות rachmanus and people sometimes they lose their right thinking. אבל, Aval,
but here the point of this is to make a contrast. אבל
זקני תורה, Aval ziknei Torah, sages of
Torah, אינם כן, einam kein, that's not what happens to them.
אלא כל זמן שמזקינין דעתן מתיישבת עליהם. Ela kol zman shemazkinin da'atan
mityashevet aleihem. The older they get, the more sort of, the more
straightforward is their thinking. They gain in sagacity and in and as
שנאמר shenemar as the verse says, בישישים חכמה Bishishim chochma in the
elders are wisdom, ואורך ימים תבונה v'orech yamim tvuna and with length
of days comes understanding. What?
I'm just thinking that Rabbi Yosef lost his learning.
I know, so obviously for medical cases of dementia presumably this was
not referring, but I think the point of it though is is
that if you're constantly exercising your brain and you're
constantly learning challenging intellectual types of things so then it keeps your
mind sharp even as you continue to get old and maybe you
even gain greater depth.
And I published three papers on that. Really? Seriously? Yeah.
And then appeared in the New
York Times and really, does that hold off like like biological like
dementia that's due to biological causes?
No, what it probably, you
also said that once it happens, it happens quicker. Once you get
dementia.
Yeah, that was the, what it probably, it probably compensates for the
biology is what we the current evidence.
Ah, you mean so that the biology could be causing some dementia
but then this activates other parts of the brain that compensate?
That's one of the theories and it's
probably a good guess.
Interesting, interesting.
So yes, James, this מסכתא, masechta, the מסכתא masechta which is a
purely intellectual exercise.
Right, so right, exactly. So what's it doing here at the מסכתא?
masechta?
I mean it's not this if we actually had a Temple this
actually would matter unlike some of the other.
Yeah, but even the scenarios are highly very rare and unlikely scenarios.
So what's it doing here? So some people just say what it's
doing here is is that since we're talking about alive is one
and dead is seven, we're talking about things that like increase as
they not exactly die, get older, but okay I think that's pretty
tenuous. I think certainly what James said like the פשט pshat like
we just went through this whole thing which was mental acrobatics and
it's actually saying, mental acrobatics is a pretty good thing anyway, keeps
your mind sharp. So that could certainly be one thing. I had
another possibility which might be a little bit a little bit of
a stretch but but the word I was thinking two things here
about like it could be a play of words because זקנים zkeinim
and זקני ziknei is almost like קינים. Kinnim. And we just actually
mentioned and we just actually mentioned seven, we actually just mentioned seven
so it's זיין zayin קינים Kinnim I don't know. That's I don't
know, maybe. And the other word is מטורפת m'terefet which means to
be mixed up. So maybe there's a little play
here what about קינים Kinnim being mixed up. I don't know. That
was that's a little speculation anyway.
So with that הדרן עלך מסכת קינים וסליקא לה מסכת קינים. Hadran
alach masechet Kinnim uslika la masechet Kinnim.
סיום. Siyum. Actually what I was thinking is that we should talk
about I הדרן עלך Hadran alach for the סיום הש"ס Siyum Hashas
but not everybody here, I mean only Charlie has done the סיום
הש"ס Siyum Hashas but we'll have done that but maybe we should
talk about doing a סיום siyum of קדשים Kodashim because that's coming
up in like a week and a half and pretty much everybody
here has seen it for all of קדשים.
Kodashim. Yeah, I think it's I think it's ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
It's about a week and a half.